<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Irish colours folded, or, The Irish Roman-Catholick's reply to the (pretended) English Protestants answer to the letter desiring a just and mercifall regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland (which answer is entitled The Irish colours displayed), addressed (as that answer and letter have been) to His Grace the Lord Duke of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of that kingdome.</title>
            <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12211463</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12211463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 904:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Irish colours folded, or, The Irish Roman-Catholick's reply to the (pretended) English Protestants answer to the letter desiring a just and mercifall regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland (which answer is entitled The Irish colours displayed), addressed (as that answer and letter have been) to His Grace the Lord Duke of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of that kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688.</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56313:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Iriſh Colours FOLDED, OR THE Iriſh Roman-Catholick's Reply</p>
            <p>To the (pretended) Engliſh Proteſtants Anſwer To the Letter <hi>deſiring a juſt and mercifull regard of the Roman Catholicks of</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>(Which Anſwer is entitled The Iriſh Colours Diſplayed.)</p>
            <p>Addreſſed (As that Anſwer and Letter have been) To his Grace The Lord Duke of ORMOND, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of that KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vince in bono malum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed in the Year 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56313:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56313:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT could hardly be imagin'd, that the Letter which I preſented to your Grace, and which I publiſhed of late, ſhould have rais'd ſo great a ſtorm againſt me for no other reaſon then that I beg'd your Grace's favor in behalf of my diſtreſſed Country, and implored the performance of publick Faith, ſhewing the miſchiefs that have followed the breach of it. This is done in the dark by an impudent aſſertor of ſtrange poſitions. But whoever he be, certainly his paſſion and immoderation ſpeaks him ignorant of the condition of the preſent Times, of the actions of former Ages, and, above all, to be a meer ſtranger to the heroick diſpoſition of <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, and utterly to forget that if it were in your Grace<hi>'s</hi> nature to entrench, for conveniencies ſake in the leaſt meaſure, upon the honor of your Maſter, or to have formed your ſelf, even by connivance, to a dexterous compliance with thoſe different parties, that made it their deſign to ruine Monarchy, you would indeed as to the quiet and ſecurity of your perſon, the temporary improvement of your int'reſt, have floated calmly on the top of every bilow raiſed by the tempeſt of thoſe evil Times. But in ſo doing, your Grace would have left ſuch a Monument to your poſterity, as you had not received from your Anceſtors, and ſuch as (although the fate of the times had excuſed it in others) was unpardonable in the Houſe of <hi>Ormond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In truth, I think there is ſomwhat more in the Letter, that tends to move pitty, and to implore Juſtice (which I conceive to be the ſcope of it) then the Reader will
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56313:3"/>
think well pay'd <hi>with that braſs penny in the heap of rubbiſh.</hi> But there are ſlights in all Arts. And this of the Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers puts me in mind how the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bolton</hi> was wont to tell that a witty Lawyer coming before him, and finding himſelf preſt with a throng of Arguments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many were unanſwerable, he ſelected the ſlighteſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that thoſe only were of moment; but as to the reſt, he would not give his Lordſhip the trouble of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon the refutation of ſuch impertinencies.</p>
            <p>But it being not my intent to perplex ſo weighty a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by deſcending after a Logical manner, to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar defects in the Anſwer, I ſhall endeavor to keep my ſelf, as near as I can, within thoſe Limits which the Anſwerers paſſion and immoderation have made him walk in: and to ſhew how amongſt all his conſiderations, he minds thoſe things leaſt on which he ſhould have beſtowed the moſt ſolid reflections.</p>
            <p>He that diſcourſes of ſetling a Kingdom under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of its natural Prince in peace and ſecurity, ſhould firſt conſider that a <hi>King</hi> is Father of his people, and that they are a portion of mankind, whereof no one is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from Rebellion againſt Heaven; that the bowels of this King's paternal love, in imitation of God, whoſe Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent he is, have compaſſion for the frailties of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and mercy for their greateſt crimes. The eldeſt on might repine at the favor done his prodigal brother, but his father made him a feaſt. Which ſhows that the affection of <hi>Princes</hi> to their Subjects in general, moves in another Orb then ours to one another. Our Intereſt may make us ſnarll; but our King is our Common Father.</p>
            <p>The want of duly weighing this principle, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility in a Prince to diveſt himſelf of this genuin and natural property of being a Father, hath afforded the Anſwerer liberty to advance ſome poſitions, that (without any juſt offence, I may ſay,) do not ſpeak him either a charitable Perſon, or a prudent States-man.</p>
            <p>The Anſwerer gives your Grace an <hi>accompt of a word or a fear which juſt then fell from him,</hi> and in truth the <hi>word</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56313:3"/>
bears in it ſelf very evident marks that it was precipitat; but how the <hi>fear</hi> could expreſs it ſelf in that language, I know not. However your Grace will conceive it a ſad and ſevere poſition, <hi>that this contention between the two parties in Ireland will never have an end.</hi> And it is no wonder <hi>your Grace ſhould ſtartle at it,</hi> if you did not conſider that the ſame God, who makes the much oppoſite qualities of the Elements agree for the conſervation of the mixt, who depreſt our King to raiſe him higher, and led him by the hand of his Providence to the Throne of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, without other ſupports then a ſenſe of their duty in his Subjects, hath ſtill a power left him <hi>to put an end to the contentions of the two parties in Ireland,</hi> and that not by the ways of his omnipotent will or miraculous actings, but by his ordinary concurrence by ſecondary Cauſes. For if His Majeſtie's clemency could make up ſo huge a breach as lay open before him by the Murder of His Father, ought we not to hope that he may be imitated by his Subjects in laying aſide that everlaſting contention to which the Anſwerer would condemn them? Shall no length of time be allowed to ſet limits to the vengeance this Anſwerer would have them to expect the one of the other? The <hi>Brittains,</hi> the <hi>Danes,</hi> the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and the <hi>Normans</hi> are now ſo incorporated in <hi>England,</hi> as the memory of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction is loſt amongſt them. Yet much blood hath been drawn in their Conteſts, and the Actions of particular Men of each of thoſe Nations have been ſuch, as they may be juſtly ſtiled Barbarous and Inhumane.</p>
            <p>Your Grace knowes with what horrour the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation looks upon thoſe Maſſacres and Murders in the North, committed in the beginning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion by the Raskal multitude upon their innocent, unwarned, and unprovided Neighbors; but the number of Two hundred thouſand, (although this Writer comes ſhort One hundred thouſand in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of what the Convention-Commiſſioners gave up to His Majeſty in their Anſwer to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Agents) is ſo exorbitantly vaſt, that a ſtranger who findes the dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Map, and underſtands this certain
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56313:4"/>
truth, That there were then in <hi>Ireland</hi> One hundred Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives for each perſon; theſe men would paſs under the notion of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, will readily conclude, That the whole <hi>Ireland</hi> is but one City ſo thronged with Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, as men cannot walk in the Streets unjuſtled.</p>
            <p>There is no man who hath a greater deteſtation for thoſe foul crimes then I have. And yet after exact enquiry, I dare averre there have been more Patritians and Knights of <hi>Rome</hi> murdered in the Conflicts and Proſcriptions between <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> within the Walls of the City, then periſhed by thoſe infamous Maſſacres throughout <hi>Ireland, In the firſt two moneths of the Rebellion.</hi> And that although the Streets were covered with <hi>Roman</hi> Carcaſſes, and the Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels ran Blood, yet a few years buried thoſe Animoſities, and both Factions lived after, as peaceably as became Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens that paid Obedience to one and the ſame Emperor. We read, that the <hi>Hugonets</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who under <hi>Francis</hi> the Second conſpired againſt the Government, and then, and in the Reign of ſeveral Kings after, were as bitterly bent againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, as the Ancient <hi>Gawls</hi> were againſt <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and where they had power left to poſterity ſtrange Monuments of their Rage and Cruelty; Yet thoſe ſo divided Affections are ſo now compoſed, as both contend who ſhall beſt ſerve their Prince, and the different Perſwaſion in Religion is ſo far from leſſening the <hi>French</hi> Kings truſt in men of Merit, that Marſhal <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein</hi> very deſervingly commands in Chief the Military Power of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> for the ſhort time of his reign had a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous party, that laid about them as barbarouſly and as inhumanely as men could do. Yet many of them were Inhabitants of that City in <hi>Germany,</hi> where Peace was ſo ſucceſsfully treated between the Empire and <hi>Sweden,</hi> and between <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland:</hi> So quiet was that place and people, then grown, that had been once ſo miſerably diſtracted.</p>
            <p>Even the <hi>Catalonians,</hi> who not many years ſince, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Dominion over them to a Foreign Prince, That
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56313:4"/>
murdered their Vice-Roy, that imbrued their hands in the blood of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Council, and all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that came in their way, and perpetrated ſuch villanies as we cannot reach to expreſs by calling them Barbarous and Inhumane: Yet His Catholick Majeſty hath ſatisfied His Juſtice with the puniſhment of the Principal Incendiaries in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Revolt &amp; having brought the people back to a due ſenſe of their Obedience, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and they fit down as amicably, and with as general confidence, the one in the other, as they did at any time before. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and out of deſire to have the Grounds of future Animoſities, utterly removed by the exemplar Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt Criminal, they have often moved, that no man on either ſide may be exempt from ſatisfying the Law for any foul Murder.</p>
            <p>Now Your Grace, who is better able to call to minde Thouſands of Examples, evidencing the little reaſon men have to deſpair of the perfect ſettlement of the moſt diſcompoſed States, and of the firm Union of different Affections, will doubtleſs conceive that to ſay, <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention between the two parties in Ireland, will never have an end,</hi> is an Aſſertion full of diffidence in Gods providence, and full of ignorance of what hath ſucceeded in this, and in former ages, upon the like occaſion.</p>
            <p>But that Your Grace may obſerve, that the Grounds whereupon this Gentleman eſtabliſheth his Prediction, are as vain and frivolous, as the Prediction it ſelf is teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarious and imprudent; I ſhall (without ſearch into the Aſpect of the Planets, or that of <hi>ſullying of the Moon,</hi> or <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encing</hi> (as he ſpeaks) <hi>that climat)</hi> deſcend to the particulars of what he conſiders in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>And firſt, he unluckily lays that for a Foundation which either muſt reſtrain all Princes from making new acquiſitions; or (if they purſue his Politick Precepts) muſt turn the Territories they have acquired by any pretence of Conqueſt, into a deſolate Wilderneſs; there being no other mean, in this new doctrine, to ſecure what they have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56313:5"/>
once gained by the juſt title of lawful Arms. Had the <hi>Romans,</hi> who for Six hundred years could not enlarge their Territory beyond the Bounds of <hi>Italy,</hi> made this their Principle, they muſt have ſpent more time in peopling then in conquering that the Seat of their Empire.</p>
            <p>Your Grace knows, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> for a long time after the firſt Colony of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> was planted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> were not onely ſtiled, but were actually enemies to thoſe that ſtrove to prevail over them. And certainly that is ſo Natural a Paſſion, as Beaſts partake with man in it: For if the Invaded and the Invader ſhould concur, as to the end of the work, what needed Contention? Yet Your Grace's famous Anceſtors that acted a principal part in ſpreading the Dominion of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> over thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Enemies, were (if our Hiſtories deceive us not) powerfully and faithfully aſſiſted by thoſe whom they had not long before ſubdued. And the ſelf-fame men that ſharply contended againſt them, were inſtrumental in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them fame, and extending the Bounds of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>His two next conſiderations concern the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colony and their Deſcendents, until the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight. Who without all doubt, were better verſed in the knowledge of thoſe after-drops that commonly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſtorm of Force and Invaſion, then not to expect and prepare themſelves for thoſe effects that for ſome time do attend the reſentment of an over-maſtered peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But it is ſtrange, that a man who would eſtabliſh a new and an unuſual method of Policy, did not conſider, that when a Nation is once generally compelled to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the commands of the prevailing Invader, all after Commotions do rather fix then unſettle the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear him ſay, That this laſt Rebellion was no after-drop, but an univerſal deluge. And this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion is thus far true, That the Laws having defined it Rebellion to raiſe Arms againſt an Authority eſtabliſhed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56313:5"/>
by the King, this cannot be denied to have been a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, the extent whereof, although it were not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, yet it ſpread it ſelf into the far greater part of the Kingdom. But all unbyaſſed men diſtinguiſh between the firſt Conſpirators (that were a handful of Hare-brain'd fellows of broken fortunes, and deſperate reſolutions, who upon the firſt noiſe of the extirpation of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their Religion, threatned to be executed by the Miniſtry of a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Army, took up Arms, and made the Crime of Rebellion more horrid by the foul actions, with which the rude multitude did aſperſe it) and the Noblemen and Gentry, with the reſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks: who being ſat in Parliament at <hi>Dublin,</hi> had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication made to them by thoſe Rebels to mediate for redreſs of their Grievances, and offered to continue their ſitting in order to their repreſſing of them; but were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued (as ſome do not ſpare to ſay) of Deſign to encreaſe the Confuſion. Which, I am ſure, was the ſucceſs of that prorogation. And I have heard a ſhrewd Argument aledged to prove, that ſuch was the intention of the Lords Juſtices, and thoſe of the then Council who favored the party op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the King in <hi>England.</hi> The truth where of none knows better then Your Grace, who made offer at the Council Board to raiſe Ten thouſand men. With which power, being aſſiſted by the Lords Juſtices, You undertook to quell thoſe Northern Rebels, and to ſettle the Peace of the Kingdom. But this being not accepted, and there appearing daily greater ſymptoms of the averſion to the ways of our late King of ever bleſſed memory, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Catholicks then took upon them for their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral defence (as they alledged) a Government in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lords Juſtices: Whoſe Authority over them, having not then been revoked by His Majeſty, they could not have declined, nor have ſet up any other of their own without His Majeſties Commiſſion, nor have entred into ſuch Confederacy without being guilty of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But for this, and crimes of this nature, Your Grace hath conveyed unto them His Majeſties Mercy in Articles
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56313:6"/>
of Peace. Whereof, becauſe they demand the benefit, they are expoſed to the <hi>odium</hi> of every perſon that detains any part of their Eſtates, by what title ſoever. Could Your Grace but remove this incompatibility between mens poſſeſſions, there would a <hi>word</hi> and a <hi>hope,</hi> as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly fal from this Gentleman, <hi>that the Contention between the two parties in Ireland</hi> might have an end to morrow.</p>
            <p>And now in my turn the Gentleman will give me leave to conſider, That the old <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Poſterity of that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colony firſt planted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> are more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his reflections, then thoſe in whoſe favor he writes. For if the greatneſs of Eſtates, that have been or may hereafter be conferred, muſt in his opinion foment irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable animoſities, there can no hope be left, that they and the ancient <hi>Iriſh</hi> can ever agree, ſince it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been maſters of the far greater part of their Country. What diſcovery the Articles of Forty eight make of their reſolution in cold blood, to unravel the ſettlement of ages paſt, I cannot conceive: Nothing appears to me in them which trenches upon His Majeſties Prerogative; nor the right which a Subject may claim to his Inheritance. The <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks do not by thoſe Articles ingroſs the places of profit, honor, and truſt to themſelves, nor impoſe the exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion upon any man of a different perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>When this Gentleman conſidered the diſſimilitude of Cuſtoms, Manners, Habit, and Language, between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> I expected he would have laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Your Grace, (who are to direct the Government of <hi>Ireland)</hi> the ways how to invite, or inforce the ruder ſort to conform themſelves in all thoſe particulars to the rules of civility of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But Your Grace will of your ſelf finde better ways, and more for His Majeſties advantage, then by diſpeopling the Kingdom, or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering the people, to communicate this happineſs unto them. Which might have been introduced long ſince, if ſome former Governors had not made it their ſtudies rather to plant their Eſtates, then cultivate their mindes.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56313:6"/>
            <p>As for the reflection which he makes upon the manner of celebrating of Funerals with howlings, which indeed is barbarous (although many in <hi>Poland</hi> and other places in the continent do ſtill continue that ſavage cuſtom) I hope your Grace, without ſending the Natives to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> or forcing them to ſuch indigence as may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to cry for Almes, will not onely ſupreſs the <hi>Ditty,</hi> if any ſuch be uſed, but ever abrogate the <hi>Tune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the conſideration which he raiſes from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon converſation of the vulgar, and their brawlings: the Petty Conſtables, and the Stocks in every Pariſh, without extirpating the Nation (for his aſſertion, <hi>That the contention between the two parties in</hi> Ireland <hi>will never ceaſe,</hi> always tends to that) will eaſe your Grace from any great affright of a diſturbance in the Government, by reaſon of the terms of <hi>malice, ſuſpition, and contempt;</hi> yea in caſe they did upbraid each other with as much acrimony, as if they were bred under the diſcipline of the Oyſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives at <hi>Billingſgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What he next adds, ſeems to have more weight in it: and I confeſs it will be worthy your Grace's care, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bring the common <hi>Iriſh</hi> to civility, which of it ſelf will rectifie any ſupine ignorance they may be guilty of in order to their incapableneſs of diſtinguiſhing what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Spiritual, what the Temporal Juriſdiction; but to give encouragement to the Roman Catholique Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to infuſe into the people a true ſenſe of the Catholique Doctrine, contained in their humble Remonſtrance, Acknowledgement, Proteſtation and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, Printed at <hi>London</hi> the third of <hi>February</hi> 1661. But this Gentleman muſt give me leave to ſay, that your Grace, who knows aſwell as any man living, the temper and inclination of that people, cannot be of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the moſt vulgar among them is perſwaded, <hi>That the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland <hi>lawfully belongs to the King of</hi> Spain. Nay, how little influence the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> or the Pope had upon them when the Peace was concluded, your Grace beſt knows, who hath found by experience, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56313:7"/>
notwithſtanding the Nuntio's Excommunication, the moſt conſiderable parts of the Nation, made way for his Majeſtie's Government over the Kingdom, and received your Grace, who was entruſted with his Majeſties autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: and notwithſtanding that ſenceleſs excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fulminated by the Prelates at <hi>James Town,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firm in their adherence to the Peace, which by your Grace was convey'd unto them from his Majeſty, and in their obedience to his Majeſtie's authority, which upon your leaving the Kingdom, your Grace did transfer to the Marqueſs of <hi>Clanrickard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which the writer of that anſwer conſiders next, and endeavors to advance for the end he aims at (which is the extirpation of the Nation) is the moſt uncharit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, the moſt unnatural, and the moſt ignoble argument that could fall from the Pen of any man that profeſſed a regard of Conſcience or Honor: And queſtionleſs did proceed from ſome perſon, that having himſelf for his conveniency, and the good of his intereſt, ſacrificed his duty to his King, when God was pleaſed in ſome ſmall meaſure to over-ballance the rights of the Crown, with the power of his prevailing enemies, wonders why all men ſhould not be ſo wiſe as to relinquiſh for the ſame ends, all Patriotſhip and ſence of their declining Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. But he little knows how unfit a perſon he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be entertained with ſo unworthy a ſuggeſtion. For if your Grace, in the Caſe of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> barely upon the ſcore of friendſhip, is ſaid to have been pleaſed to anſwer a perſon of quality, who laid before you the great hazard you run in, ſpeaking ſo freely of that great man's merit, and juſtifying his innocence, at a time when the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> was ſo highly incenſed againſt him, That if his head were upon the block, you would profeſs him your friend: can this writer hope that your Grace, who ſo early in your youth cheriſh't a particular friendſhip with ſo much courage and gallantry, will not think it a baſe and abject part in the few of the Nobility and Gentry now in the City of <hi>London,</hi> to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56313:7"/>
               <hi>with ſaving their own ſtake, and leave ſtickling in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage and defence of their common Country?</hi> But however they may be <hi>leſſened in the Gentlemans value,</hi> for perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, which is an indiſpenſable duty they owe to their Country, and to thoſe that juſtly may claim benefit of the peace in it; yet they could not (in my opinion) have otherwiſe prevented the clamor of all men of honor, nay of all mankind againſt them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He conſiders that this <hi>enmity,</hi> which he calls <hi>implacable, of the Iriſh to the Engliſh, ſprings from the ſame root with that of all other ſubjected people to their Conquerors,</hi> and gathers for proof thereof the miſchief befaln the Roman Citizens in the leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> on the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> and on the <hi>Danes</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and yet forbears to mind your Grace that the <hi>Normans</hi> were Conquerors as well as they, and have to this day preſerved their acquiſitions in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have done in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince their firſt deſcent in that Kingdom, by thoſe means which have made the work laſting, without breaking for convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, thoſe limits which Mercy, Juſtice, and Honor, puts to all humane actions. Herein the carriage of your Grace's famous Anceſtors, will better inſtruct you then the Politicks of any intereſted perſon. And your Grace having conformed your ſelf to the rules preſcribed by Mercy, Juſtice, and Honor, what need <hi>the ballancing inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts between Engliſh and Iriſh, or boying up either of them?</hi> The Country muſt at length give denomination to all that inhabit it: and the poſteriry of thoſe that proclaim lowdly the Engliſh intereſt, muſt within an age, admit themſelves to be called Iriſh as well as the Deſcendants from the firſt Colony of Engliſh planted in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs your Grace's firſt care will be to ſecure his Majeſtie's intereſt in that Kingdom, and to provide that nothing remain, which under the title of diverſity of intereſts, may prevent all mens affections from meeting in the center of his Majeſties ſervice. And your next will be to convey to ſucceeding ages, the bleſſings of that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56313:8"/>
peace, which his Majeſty after ſo evil times, and ſo many ſufferings hath given his three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And now your Grace will give me leave to conſider, that this man of ſeparation, in flat oppoſition to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties paternal and prudent deſire, ſo frequently and ſo fully expreſſed in his Letters, in his Proclamations, in his Diſcourſes, both publique and private, to have all ſeeds of animoſities utterly extinguiſhed, imploys his talent wholly in making himſelf the Trumpet of mens animoſities: and leaſt, time ſhould mitigate them, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them everlaſting. But your Grace hath more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence for things recommended with that earneſtneſs to his people by your great Maſter, then to countenance what he prohibits, or to favor thoſe uncharitable requeſts that oppoſe his commands.</p>
            <p>My Lord, It ſhall ſuffice me inſtead of all vindication, that I perſwade my ſelf your Grace believes that I am in my nature as averſe <hi>from cogging</hi> or <hi>clawing,</hi> as the Letter in it ſelf, is far from expreſſing any ſuch humor in me. But men that have an inclination to be bitter rather then fail of exerciſing their faculty, will create themſelves a ſubject. And he that takes the Nations hope, to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by your Grace, for a complement, knows little of the intereſt you have in them, and of the affection they bear you.</p>
            <p>Now, without contending in a caſe ſo little diſputable whoſe you are, I ſhall conjure your Grace, not by his Majeſties favor, and the ways to preſerve it; not by the means to prefer your children, and to encreaſe your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; nor by thoſe other politick conſiderations held forth by the Writer of that anſwer: but by the mercy and honor of his Majeſty; by the nobleneſs of your own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; by the conſtancy of the Nation in their ſufferings under your Graces command at home, and their wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings in waiting on his Majeſties fortunes abroad; by the memory of your Anceſtors that have been ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of oppreſſion, as petty Freeholders have held for many deſcents and ſtill do enjoy, ſome two, ſome four
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56313:8"/>
Acres, and others more or leſs, in the midſt of your demeaſnes, untouch'd by them, or by you, in ſo long a tract of time: by theſe I conjure your Grace ſo to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conveniency, as it may not overthrow his Majeſtie's promiſe, and ſo to be friend the intereſt of the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as, the proprietors may receive the benefit of his Majeſties mercy extended to them in Articles of Peace.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe conteſts that conſiſt of recriminations, I deſire never to engage in them. But this Writer muſt not therefore think he may be at liberty to fill the ears of his Reader, with the vaſt ſound of two hundred thouſand, and enlarge the horror of the action, by ſuppreſſing the truth, and adding Ciphers to enlarge the number. And truely had this Writer forborn in ſo deſpicable and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percilious a manner to ſpurn at the Nation, by ſaying, <hi>That the Birds, no not the Flies contributed leſs to his Majeſties Reſtauration then the Roman Catholickes in</hi> Ireland, I ſhould not have put him in mind that the Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> found not a concurrence ſo general (I mean in the Army) (for the people of <hi>England,</hi> both Proteſtant and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, opened their hearts in prayers to God and their arms to receive him) as he owes not the glorious ſucceſs of his Actions more to the dexterity of his conduct, then the ſtrength of his party. And as to that general concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in <hi>Ireland, Ludlow</hi> and Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> may tell him how difficult the work had been, but that they were taken napping. No man will ſay that an unarmed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, diſpoſed throughout the Goals of the Kingdom upon every rumor that was ſpread of any attempt to be made by his Majeſty for recovery of his right, could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed other then by their prayers to his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration. And in truth it is ſome mark of Ingenuity in this Writer, that he endeavors not to perſwade us that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> did not ſo much as pray for the Reſtauration of his Majeſty. And no Church will deny that prayers are always good, and ſometimes effectual.</p>
            <p>I do not repine at the Act of Indempnity, granted by the King. And certain I am that his Majeſty, whoſe bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56313:9"/>
of mercy could begin at that end, will in his own good time enlarge it to all his Subjects of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And I hope that when it is better underſtood in what nature the Roman Catholicks depend upon the Pope, there will be no cauſe to reproach them for their tenets in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, although they modeſtly refuſe to inveſt in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty a power of adminiſtring the Sacraments, which this zealous Gentleman, <hi>by his dependence upon his Majeſty in all Eccleſiaſtical matters,</hi> acknowledges to be in him.</p>
            <p>Although the Writer in his next Paragraph, purſuing his ordinary method of railing wittyries, ſpeaks of a ſhew <hi>of adherence to the King, which was the next covert they ſhrunk under for ſhelter;</hi> yet I muſt confeſs it will be hard to perſwade me that the beſt and moſt natural ſhelter for a Subject faln from his obedience, is not the protection of his Soveraign, and the remiſſion of his crimes. And I cannot but ſay that the world would be much deceived in that opinion they conceive of your wiſdom, if your Grace had ſuffered your ſelf to be deluded by a ſhew of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> adhereing to the King. Perhaps they fought and were killed in a dream, and that the dints the Bullets made in your Armor, while your Grace having acted all the parts of a General, expoſed your ſelf as a common ſouldier to prevent the defeat at <hi>Rathmines,</hi> were the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Iriſh Flies,</hi> whereof the Writer makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Your Grace beſt knows, in defence of whoſe cauſe you led that Army. And I dare ſwear Sir <hi>William Vaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Aſtowne,</hi> and many more of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commanders that loſt themſelves in defence of it, would not have been ſo prodigal of their lives to juſtifie <hi>Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Rebels againſt the Engliſh,</hi> and that Nation and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And that Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> Sir <hi>John Stevens, Treſwell, Travers, Wogan, Biron, Ballard,</hi> &amp;c. had not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone the hardſhip, or the mainfold hazards they did, to maintain the quarrel. And I likewiſe <hi>leave to your Graces remembrance,</hi> how great a Friendſhip and confidence there was grown, by your powerful influence upon both parties between them and the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> Which received not the leaſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56313:9"/>
diminution before the defection of thoſe that betrayed their truſt and his Majeſtie's Intereſt in <hi>Cork, Youghall, Kinſale,</hi> and the reſt of the ſtrong holds in <hi>Munſter.</hi> Who theſe were, is known to all parties in that Nation, and you can certifie my Lord, they were not <hi>Iriſh</hi> nor Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. Neither did this occaſion leſſen the eſteem, which thoſe, who by power derived from your Grace, had the principal truſt in the Nation. But your Grace, who doubtleſs did then foreſee of what uſe men of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al principles would in future times be to his Majeſty, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving provided for their ſafty, diſmiſſed them at a time when many accidents, and much refractorineſs concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to weigh down the ſcales of his Majeſtie's declining af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Yet your Grace diſmiſſed them after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as ſhewed the Roman Catholicks were very ſenſible of the loſs they were to receive by their abſence, and the many good ſervices they had joyntly performed under your Grace's command.</p>
            <p>I muſt now forbear to give your Grace any further trouble <hi>concerning any ſhred of this work,</hi> which this Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſays, <hi>he hath taken to pieces.</hi> And to do him right, I think he hath unrip'd the skirts; but he leaves the Doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let entire. And we are now as wiſe as we were before, and as far from knowing the true value of the Stuff, or what it is lin'd with, ſave that we gather by it that ſelf intereſt is a rapid Torrent that bears all down before it; and a paſſion that blinds us into a belief that nothing which advances our ends can be diſhonorable, imprudent, or unjuſt And this makes the Writer to pray in the behalf of the <hi>Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> that under that covert he or his friends may poſſeſs undiſturb'd, ſome honeſt mens Eſtates in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But that Nation, whereof he ſeems to be, have made and for ever will make it their ſtudy to preſerve their Dominion by following thoſe principles of Honor, and Juſtice, which have made their Anceſtors famous, and have obtained of God for them, the Reſlauration of ſo unparallel'd a King without blood, or the miſeries of War: and that at a time, when all disbanded Armies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56313:10"/>
of Europe, expected but a call to enrich themſelves with their ſpoils. Yet if the Nation of <hi>England</hi> ſhould even in their wiſh remit any part of thoſe principles, the obſervance whereof was ſo propitious to them and their Country, doth this Writer conceive they would not conſider what ſett of people they were to introduce, or whom they were to oppreſs? Would they think it to be an eſſential part of the intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Huſon</hi> the Cobler (ſuppoſe him free of that execrable crime of Regicide) ſhould enjoy ſix or ſeven thouſand pounds <hi>per ann.</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that ſo many families deſcended from the Ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colony, that had a ſhare in enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conqueſts and the fame of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be extirpated and forc'd to beg their bread? Or that three or four men ſhould by clandeſtine bargains, at deſpicable rates, acquire titles to the poſſeſſions, and pretences of ſuch kind of perſons who were conſcious to themſelves of their incapacity to be countenaneed by the Nation of <hi>England,</hi> in advancing even by juſt means an <hi>Engliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> and ſuddainly grow to be Cedars, that were but the underwood of the Forreſt<hi>:</hi> while thoſe that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this four hundred years, the Intereſt of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by the inference which this witty Gentleman makes to be <hi>cleavers of wood and drawers of water?</hi> No, no. That Nation is too noble, and too juſt to patronize ſuch requeſts: and they have a horror for ſuch tenets. And your Grace will give me leave to ſay that thoſe principles of Juſtice and Loyalty which you have received from your Anceſtors, which you have practiced your ſelf, and your Children by their own natural inclinations, and your Grace's example, are imbued with, and which will be conveyed from hand to hand to your poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have been, and will be the ſole fortreſs that could or may defend your family from the wrath or <hi>a more ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Maſter, then now you have the happineſs to ſerve.</hi> Pawns and pledges in <hi>England,</hi> alas, are but a Cobweb-wrought-defence for a perſon whom ſo great a Monarch would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56313:10"/>
ruine. He that holds the hearts of Princes in his hands, can beſt and will protect thoſe that are faithfull to his Vicegerent on Earth, how ſuſpitious ſoever he may be, ſo they make it their next care to be Juſt to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and redeem them from oppreſſion, if they have power.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe Texts of Scriptures, when it ſhall be made appear to me, that they are miſcited, miſconſter'd or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applied, no humane reſpect ſhall make me oppugne truth<hi>:</hi> and the ſame obligation is upon me not to deſert it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> Theſe are the brief Animadverſions, I thought fit, to give at this time on the <hi>Iriſh Colours Diſplayed:</hi> ſuch as indeed my other, although little and private, yet neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary diſtractions, gave me the opportunity to perfect; and which your Grace's moſt weighty, manifold and publick may afford you the leaſure to peruſe: having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe by me, however yet unperfected, a more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and more exact reply to all the particulars of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, unchriſtian and very unreaſonable piece. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I take notice of his <hi>Motto;</hi> his <hi>pretence;</hi> his epithets of <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> wherewith he would flatter me; his <hi>great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; juſtice of his caſe;</hi> his Ink or black, and the <hi>Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> colour he would make ours; the <hi>Pamphlet;</hi> his <hi>difficulty to finde the matter of it,</hi> and <hi>the eaſineſſe to anſwer;</hi> his <hi>braſse penny in a heap of rubbiſh;</hi> his labour to put out your eys and your judgment too, by endeavouring to perſwade the matter of my letter could <hi>be hardly felt in your hand;</hi> his <hi>little game;</hi> his <hi>planets</hi> and <hi>chaffering vein;</hi> his <hi>unhappy engraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch numbers of old Engliſh Families upon the Iriſh ſtock and Intereſt;</hi> his impoſing on and abuſing <hi>of</hi> Spencer's <hi>View;</hi> his next Paragraph after, of <hi>Spaniſh Papiſts;</hi> his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at <hi>our ſtickling</hi> one for another, deſiring juſtice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fundamental laws of both Kingdomes, and his Majeſties gracious Promiſes and Conceſſions; and yet his inconſequence in the 15. page of his Anſwer, in <hi>ſtickling</hi> himſelf for all his own gang, without exception of any, and in a cauſe of manifeſt in juſtice, even againſt all laws both divine and humane; his <hi>ſomething more;</hi> his <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling;</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56313:11"/>
his <hi>cogging and clawing,</hi> and unfortunate proofs thereof, <hi>your conſtant believers, your paſſionate ſticklers, &amp;c.</hi> his impoſture with charging me to have <hi>threatned your fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would leſſen your dependencies, </hi> his malicious applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my example of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> even againſt his own knowledg, and the whole deſigne and expreſſe tenour of my Letter in the beginning, proſecution and ending of it; his groſſe, wilfull and affected ignorance (or diſſimulation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) of not knowing <hi>how the</hi> Iriſh <hi>came to be your brethren upon any other kindred:</hi> his minding <hi>you of your Anceſtors and your own unſhaken loyalty to the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>and of your conſtancy to the old Proteſtant Religion,</hi> ſo imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the end he drove at; his own ſervile flatteries; his unbelieved <hi>affections to, or confidence in you;</hi> his love to his <hi>miſtreſſe;</hi> the <hi>forced or feigned ſmiles</hi> he would attribute to you; and the ſullen <hi>aking jealouſies</hi> of himſelf and his party; thoſe paſſages, <hi>without being too much envied and ſome thing feared,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>a teſtimony and a pawn of your Families Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>how much the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation might be eſtranged from you by your favour to the</hi> Iriſh, &amp;c. <hi>ſuddenly either forgiven in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or forgotten upon earth;</hi> his <hi>bold ſlander;</hi> his <hi>Ravilliack</hi> and <hi>perhaps half a doozen Jeſuites, and perhaps half a dozen more with</hi> Cromwel <hi>and</hi> Ireton, and <hi>his outward compliance, &amp;c.</hi> his <hi>Birds, Flyes and bare intentions;</hi> his unreaſonable diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence twixt <hi>ſtanding on Articles,</hi> and <hi>Claiming his Majeſtie's Grace held forth in the Act of Indemnity;</hi> his <hi>not queſtioning but the ſame reaſons which then induced His Majeſty to grant it them and deny it us, continue ſtill, and will doe ſo to both our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities;</hi> his <hi>Long Parliament's, and the following tyrannous Powers quarrel purſued againſt the</hi> Iriſh; his <hi>not allowing theſe had fought ſo long</hi> (that is, ſince the peace made with your Grace) <hi>for the King;</hi> his having <hi>never heard,</hi> and his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>none can believe, the overpowering them with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes,</hi> and he muſt mean <hi>then</hi> (if he ſpeak to purpoſe) when the laſt towns and places of <hi>Ireland</hi> were given up: his quitting the field, and running away, and giving up the quarrel, in the next paragraph 14. page of his book, where, in effect, he not only acknowledges no anſwer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56313:11"/>
by him to my letter; but in plain terms tels your Grace ſo much, that <hi>for matter of</hi> our <hi>Articles in Forty eight, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the writer of that Letter preſſes to be obſerved, that of Tranſplanſplantation, Corporations, &amp; the diſpoſall of the Iriſh lands, &amp;c they are particulars</hi> he <hi>will not meddle with;</hi> and yet theſe are all the particulars of that Letter, he would ſeem otherwiſe, or at leaſt was concernd to Anſwer; his reflection after this, on that paſſage of mine which relates to the <hi>Engliſh Army</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as then compoſed; and his confidence in them; his <hi>other-ſhred,</hi> or <hi>will couched threatnings;</hi> his other <hi>truth,</hi> which yet hath nothing more than untruth; his evill Counſel, immediately following; his declining the <hi>parrallel,</hi> and his flat refuſing to anſwer at <hi>the weapon</hi> of holy Scripture (although he brags it might be eaſily done) or try the juſtice of our quarrel thereby; which manifeſtly convinces him to have little of an <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant,</hi> or indeed a Chriſtian in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he withall undertakes the patronage of ſuch a cauſe, or the defence of it in point of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which a little before, that is, in his 15. page, he obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges himſelf unto; Laſtly, the impertinency of his whole diſcourſe, if conſidered as an anſwer, having not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any one argument of all my Letter; not even, with ſatisfaction to the Reader, any one of thoſe very immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial paſſages he ſingled out; but above all, the cloſe and farr yet more dangerous deſign this Gentleman drives, (under that which is more overt in his paper) to create new troubles to our Gracious King, to involve his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in bloody confuſions again, and even to deſtroy his Sacred Majeſty at laſt by ruining firſt, and for ever, thoſe that have for ſo many years, and doe yet ſuffer for him. My Lord, of all theſe and what ever elſe is regardable in his Anſwer, I take a more particular and more exact no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in ſome papers, I have by me, then I can here; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my other occaſions will not yet ſerve me to finiſh them as I would; nor yours (I ſuppoſe) your Grace to read them at this time.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56313:12"/>
            <p>However, my Lord, that reall and dutifull affection, which penn'd my former Letter, gives in the mean time this. And withall craves your pardon; if I minde you here, thoſe truly ſage, divine precepts, which this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle politick ſpirit of earth ſeem'd not to be verſed in, or at leaſt either contemns or neglects. For indeed my Lord he appears to me all along his writing, of the number of thoſe who ſee heaven, and all the hopes of the other life, as Mathematicians make us behold in a dark Chamber, whatſoever paſſeth abroad, through a little crany, in ſuch a manner, that all things we ſee, appear like ſhadows and landskips turned topſie-turvy. Verily, I take this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to be abuſed ſo by himſelf. And that after he hath ſtopped up all the Windows and acceſſes to heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rayes, he hath made a little hole for the Moon, and all the bleſſings of the other life have ſeemed very ſlender to his diſtruſtfull ſpirit: and that he hath put on a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to make a fortune at what price ſoever, and to build on earth like <hi>Cain,</hi> after he hath almoſt renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the hopes of heaven. Behold, the reaſon why, with ſo little regret or ſhame, he adventures to lay maximes before you, that ſuppoſe to hold on a courſe in all affaires and Governments of the world, which may be crafty, captious, worldly, unjuſt, yea cruel too, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane (when it is for their intereſt) and a courſe (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) which may be alwayes independent of divine laws, if not for ſome popular apparence</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, the proofs you have conſtantly given of your chaſt apprehenſions of a God, and a Providence ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Univerſe, of a ſtrong vertue, and a reſolution firm, unchangable therein, both in your proſperous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, as well now as heretofore, and in that condition, which hath been ſo long moſt adverſe, and hath tryed you like gold in the Furnace, together with your two great ſucceſſive Masters on earth (whom you have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved moſt faithfully in all changes, and in obedience to that heavenly One, whom all Servants and Maſters too muſt revere) make all that know you well, be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56313:12"/>
this Enchanter hath laboured in vain to charm you. And me no leſſe, That you had rather take your maximes, and meaſures, and rules, and examples of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from the Oracles of God, from the equity of the Laws, from the dictates of your own ſevere Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and from the model of ſo many great, honourable and holy Stateſmen, who flouriſhed in the ſucceſſion of all Ages, and govern'd ſuccesfully their people, then from the vain illuſions and wicked policy of a <hi>Machiavel</hi> or <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or from the diaſtrous undertakings, and ſad Cataſtrophe, of either themſelves, or of thoſe they tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tord.</p>
            <p>Never was there a more refined wit then <hi>Achitophel,</hi> of whom the Scripture ſaid, <hi>Conſilium Achitophel, quaſi ſi quis conſuleret Deum, That men conſulted with him as with a God:</hi> Yet never was there any more unhappy in his practice. For having diſpoſed of the affairs of the Kingdom, and thoſe of his own houſe, there remaining none to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for but his own perſon, he took a halter, and hang'd himſelf, becauſe they approved not one of his Counſels. Nor ever was any more unhappy then <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel</hi> in all his enterprizes, notwithſtanding his great liſt of refined precepts. And for thoſe two unfortunate Princes, that were Schollars or patterns to them, <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and Duke <hi>Valentinois</hi> (beſides hundreds more that would not be wiſe by their fate) we know what end they had. Beſides, my Lord, you conſider it hath been the judgemet, neer two thouſand years ago, even of that very great Polititian <hi>Thucidides,</hi> and ever ſince a general obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it is to day, of all well underſtanding men, that thoſe curious wits, deſpoiled of the fear of God, have alwayes been moſt turbulent and unhappy in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage both of their own affairs and the publick alſo: As on the contrary, thoſe who had not ſo much knowledge and invention, but purſued the general inſtinct of God, have held their Eſtates better govern'd in ſimplicity, more proſperous in the ignorance of evil, and much more in the laſting of their felicity.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:56313:13"/>
            <p>And your own reading can furniſh you with ſufficient proofs, that ordinarily the moſt unhappy among States have been thoſe, who have made the greateſt ſhew of knowledge, to deceive under humane Policy. That is it which overthrew the Commonwealth of the <hi>Athenians.</hi> That which ruined the houſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who, revolting againſt his Prince, having raiſed a State by ambition, and a Religion out of phantaſie, having ſeen the Altas crack with the horror of his crimes, and his heart ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more obdurate then ſtone, in the end he is ſo chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the hand of God, that there was not left ſo much as one handful of duſt of his houſe upon the face of the earth. <hi>Domus Jeroboam everſa eſt &amp; deleta de ſuperſicie terrae.</hi> And even that which undid the very firſt King of Gods own election. For this unfortunate Prince, while he makes ſhew punctually to obey the Law of God, under the direction of <hi>Samuel,</hi> but afterwards learns to become cunning, envious, faithleſs, plotting deſignes, conſulting Pythoneſſes, and ſeeking in all points his own petty intereſts<hi>:</hi> poor <hi>David</hi> (whoſe life this King judged, without any other cauſe but envy, incompatible with his own eſtate) diſmounts him, uſing no other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, but that of making himſelf an honeſt man</p>
            <p>Holy Scripture, and other Monuments of latter and former times, can further tell your Grace, that conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many other Politicians, who made profeſſion to refine all the world, who attempted to practice, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own vain Idea's, either you have ſeen but the firſt ſtation of their plaiſtered felicity, or have ever found great labyrinths, horrible confuſions, fortunes little laſting, dejection in their poſterity, hatred, and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of Ages.</p>
            <p>And that you may without enquiry or trouble to your thoughts behold with a ready eye, how there is no poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy powerful againſt God, and how he ſurpriſeth the moſt ſubtle, making ſnares of their greateſt cunning to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive them, ſee (my Lord) in the book of <hi>Heſter,</hi> that wicked <hi>Aman,</hi> the great Favourite of <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ho pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56313:13"/>
as our Gentleman doth, the ruine of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> who prevailed ſo far, as to have the lots caſt, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> warrants ſign'd, and proclamation made thereof in <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan,</hi> and a day prefixed for the general ſlaughter of that Nation, young and old, men, women, and children, and Courriers diſpatch'd to all Provinces of the Empire, to command the execution, while theſe forlorn people, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed as they were then among ſtrangers, moved hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth to pity with their yellings, becauſe they ſaw not how the Decree was avoidable; ſee this wicked <hi>Aman</hi> reſolved on ſo horrid an act as was the deſtruction of ſo many millions, and reſolved upon it only to be revenged on <hi>Mordecai</hi> that ſaved the King from murder, and, after this, to raiſe himſelf with the wealth of the deſtroyed (all which the King beſtowed upon him at the ſame time.) See this Politician of Hell, yea notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his power and favour, ruin'd in a moment, yea within three dayes after the Decree publiſhed, and ruin'd by this very <hi>Mordecai,</hi> a contemptible worm of the earth, till then, in <hi>Amans</hi> apprehenſion. See preſently a countermand of the bloody Edicts; <hi>Aman</hi> forced to lead <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s horſe, and cry him in the ſtreets of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan</hi> the greateſt Lord of the Empire, next the King; and himſelf next day after raiſed indeed, but on a gibbet of fifty cubits high, to humble him for ever, by the moſt ignominious death could be: while the Jews on that very day, by him deſigned for utter deſtruction, ſaw themſelves maſters, and (even by the Kings command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all his Lieutenants and other Subjects) execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, in the Kings own Court <hi>Suſan,</hi> of the ten ſons of their great enemy, and of eight hundred more, two dayes continually; and in other Provinces, throughout the Empire, of threeſcore and fifteen thouſand men, who had before conſpired againſt them with <hi>Aman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, my Lord, ſee one example more very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent in the book of <hi>Exodus.</hi> Behold <hi>Pharaoh</hi> turn'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, and forgetful of all the obligations laid by <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> on him. See this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> becoming crafty, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56313:14"/>
thinking by ruinating the Iſraelits his Scepter is through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed. But ſee withall how God ſurprizeth him in his ſubtilty, and makes him know the oppreſſion of this poor people is the inſtrument of his ruine. A little child, which lyeth floating on the waters of <hi>Nilus</hi> in a cradle of bulruſhes, as a worm hidden in ſtraw, and whoſe afflicted mother meaſureth his tomb with her eyes in every billow of this faithleſs element, is delivered from peril by the very blood of <hi>Pharao,</hi> to turn the Diadem of <hi>Pharao</hi> into duſt, and bury him with all his Nobles, and an army of two hundred thouſand men with him, as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> writes, all enflamed in a gulph of the red Sea.</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, I have almoſt forgot my ſelf, being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported on this ſubject, whereon the temerity of my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer hath engaged me to dilate: not that I would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct your Grace by theſe examples of Gods confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil Counſels, whom I know to need no ſuch anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes againſt the poiſon of this Writer, but that I might convince, or confound him.</p>
            <p>I know your Grace deſires rather I ſhould minde your ſelf thoſe Maximes, or Precepts, and Examples too, that may confirm you in a reſolution to be throughly vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to be exactly juſt and benignly merciful (being Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Mercy are the Vertues, above all others, muſt be moſt proper to your great charge:) then ſuch as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie againſt the Vices oppoſite, from which you are by Nature and Education wholly eſtranged.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I ſhall then, to that purpoſe, call to your memory, in the firſt place, three paſſages of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. The firſt is a Maxime of the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Ghoſt, by the mouth of the wiſeſt King, or man, amongſt the children of men; and you may read it in the ſixteenth Chapter of <hi>Solomons Proverbs. Juſtitia firmatur ſolium.</hi> It is an abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Kings to commit wickedneſs, <hi>for the throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe.</hi> My Lord, even that very Throne, for which you have undergone ſo many labours, hardſhips and hazards theſe twenty yeares paſt, &amp; for the fixing of which, you are now to undertake the greateſt charge that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56313:14"/>
can be laid upon you, and the moſt difficult to perform wil be eſtabliſhed by doing juſtice. The ſecond is an admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the ſame Holy Spirit (even to your ſelf) by the month of Jeſus the Son of <hi>Syrach. Noli quaerere fieri Iudex niſi juſtitia valeas irrumpere iniquitatem: ne forte extimeſcas faciem potentis, &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nas ſcand lum in aequitate tua Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> 7. <hi>Seek not to be judge, if you have not the power to break tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row all iniquity: leſt any time you feare the perſon of the Mighty, and lay a ſtumbling-block in the way of your uprightneſſe.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, my Lord, this Text imports a <hi>ſeeking,</hi> and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the literal rigour of that firſt word, it is onely againſt ſuch; and therefore, inſomuch, not properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to your Grace. But you know, my Lord, as well, by natural reaſon, as by forty clear paſſages of Holy Bible, the duty of doing juſtice is nothing leſſe incumbent on Judges or Governours, that by injunction or command, they undergo their charge: it being evident that none may tye our conſcience to act unrighteouſly, and that contrariwiſe by that very command to accept the charge, the obligation to be juſt is the greater, if this may admit of any encreaſe. Which is the reaſon I averre the wiſe man ſpeaks, even in this very paſſage, directly to your Grace, adviſing you either to have ſufficient power and a vertuous conſtant reſolution to beat down, trample under foot all obſtacles, even that regard of the Powerful or Mighty, which might otherwiſe hinder you from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtice indifferently to all perſons in your great charge: or certainly to lay down (at his Majeſty's feet) your Commiſſion, leaſt otherwiſe it might be a ſcandall to you, an occaſion to loſe the favour of Heaven, and the repute you have hitherto preſerved ſo entire on earth, as hereditary to your Noble Houſe &amp; Family. And yet I alledg not this paſſage, as having the leaſt fear of your being hereafter unjuſt, or the leaſt hopes that any man living is ſo fit for that charge as your ſelf, under our gracious Soveraigne, in the preſent conjuncture, nor ſo deſired of all the different parties in that Nation; but that I would minde you of it as very uſefull againſt this man of ſin,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56313:15"/>
who would have you buoy up one Intereſt wholly, that is the ſtrong and prevalent, and ſink utterly the other, againſt all Divine and Humane Laws. The third paſſage, and very conſequent to this, is a queſtion, which it ſeems to me, I hear God himſelf demanding of you here, by his afflicted Prophet, <hi>Job</hi> 40. c. <hi>Si habes brachium ſicut Deus? &amp; voce ſimili tonas?</hi> Have you the arm of God? or can you thunder with a voice like his? My Lord, if this Arm, and this Voice, has been ever yet neceſſary to any man going to command a Countrey of iron and ire, a people that have not theſe many yeares diſtinguiſhed betwixt Might and Right, ſo many different parties, and as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite one to another in their demands and their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, as Eaſt and Weſt, the South and North are, it muſt be to your Grace. And therefore, my good Lord, it is but your duty to beg of God in humble prayer, that he will give you both, in that proportion and reſpect any mortal can, and one of your Place ought to have them, to overcome ſo many difficulties and oppoſitions which lye before you.</p>
            <p>In the next place, my Lord, I ſhall mind your Grace of what you know your ſelf already, That you ſhall behold under your Government a very great number of ſimple, poor, innocent, and moſt afflicted crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if any ſuch be in the whole world. And that you are to think that God hath principally created you, and hitherto preſerved you amidſt ſo many dangers, and now at laſt inſpired our gracious King to ſend you, for them. And therefore that your greateſt care muſt be to open to them your heart with an amorous compaſſion, extend to them the bowels of your charity, ſtretch out affectionately to them your helpfull hands take their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, lend ear to their cryes, cauſe their affaires to be ſpeedily diſpatched, not drawing them along in delayes which may devoure them, ſtrengthen your arm againſt thoſe that oppreſſe them, redeem the prey out of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons throat, and the Harpie's talons.</p>
            <p>For this it is, my Lord, that Kings, Princes, States and Governours are made. To actions of this kind it is, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56313:15"/>
God promiſeth all the bleſſings of Heaven, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of earth. For this ſort of proceſſes are Crownes of Glory prepared. By this means a man diveth into the bottom of the heart, and good opinion of people. This is the cauſe that one hath ſo many ſouls and lives at command, as there are men, who the more ſweetly breath aire by the liberality wherewith they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>And believe it, my Lord, your Greatneſſe, before God, will not be to multiply titles of Honour and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (which yet have followed you ſtill, as the ſhadow doth the body, and were moſt deſervedly and moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put upon you by His moſt Sacred Majeſty that now is, and by his Father of glorious memory) nor will be to cover the earth with Armies, and make rivers of blood, and to raiſe up mountaines of dead bodies; but to doe juſtice to a poor Orphan, to wipe away the teares of a forlorn Widow, to ſteep in Oyle (as the Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) the yoke of people which live on gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, who ſigh under neceſſities almoſt unſupportable to the moſt ſavage, who daily charge eares with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints &amp; altars with vowes for their deliverance, &amp; who cry for your Grace at this time as the Fathers of the old Teſtament did for the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> or as the unborn children of that very Nation are ſaid in <hi>Venerable Bede,</hi> to have done 1200. years ago, to Him that redeemed them, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, from the ſlavery of Heatheniſme, and power of Devils.</p>
            <p>But when ſhall we expect that deliverance, if not now? Now that our good King is reſtored by ſo many miracles and wonders; now that he is eſtabliſhed by all that may concur to fix his Throne; now that he is ſo well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to juſtice, and to mercy both (as he hath ever been) now that he hath neer his perſon a Councel ſo ſage, a Parliament ſo zealous for the publick good, ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable men endowed with ſo ſincere intentions; and now that your Grace is (the ſecond or third time) Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ready to part hence to your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56313:16"/>
charge, when may we reaſonably expect the comfort of that oppreſſed people, if not at this hour, when miſeries are eminent, clamours piercing, and diſpoſitions very good? Alas<hi>!</hi> my Lord, if there be any thing in the world, wherein you may be ſeen to oblige the preſent, and repleniſh future times with admiration of your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, it is in effecting this, for which Heaven is in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation and the hands of a million of poor diſconſolate ſouls are daily lifted to God.</p>
            <p>Remember, my Lord, that ſuch, and ſo many great Governours, for not having had any other aim in char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but the accommodation of their own affaires, have paſſed away like phantaſmes, leaving nought here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them but ordure, nor bearing any thing with them into the other world but crimes And that they have found that the ſould of the wounded have cryed to Heaven againſt them, and that God hath not let it paſs without revenge. <hi>Anima vulneratorum clamavit ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, &amp; Deus inultam abire non patitur,</hi> as holy <hi>Job</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the 24th. chapter, where he at large explicateth both the calamity of the poore, and the chaſtiſement of the rich that oppreſſe them.</p>
            <p>Conſider, on the other ſide, that all thoſe who have conſtantly addicted themſelves to the maintenance of Juſtice, and the conſolation of affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted perſons, beſides the Crownes which they enjoy in Heaven, live gloriouſly in the memory of men. Their mouths, which are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for juſtice, after they are ſhut up as Temples, are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worthy to have Lillies and Roſes ſtrewed on the Marble which encloſeth them; and that their poſterity alſo may reap the good odour of their noble Anceſtors, which hath made it march with up-reared head before the face of the people.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, my Lord, notwithſtanding the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer's quarrel againſt holy Scripture, to direct State-affaires, and fortifie or clear diſputes in matters of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Juſtice (which is the moſt unreaſonable ſaying could proceed from a Chriſtian; ſince if they be of any uſe at all,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56313:16"/>
they muſt be in State-affaires moſt of all others) I moſt humbly and moſt earneſtly recommend this Book of books to your Grace, whereby to guide your ſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in your moſt important determinations of State, for what may relate to right and the law of God. Look upon it as the pillar of clouds and flames, which condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the army of the living God. There it is where you ſhall learn true maximes of State, ſcored out with moſt vigorous reflections of the Wiſdome of God: and where you ſhall trample under foot, with a generous contempt, ſo many illuſions, which wretched ſoules ſeek for in the mouth of Sorcerers. Read the book of Wiſdome, the Prophets, the book of holy <hi>Job,</hi> and the Divine Pſalms of the King, choſen out according to God's own heart. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſtream of ſo many Hiſtories, written in this Theatre of wonders, which are characters of fire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the divine Providence is pleaſed to be figured to mortal eyes, that we may learn the puniſhment of crimes and the crowns of vertue.</p>
            <p>Repreſent unto your ſelf often in your idaeae's, thoſe great States-men, who have flouriſhed in the courſe of all ages: and derive light and fire from their examples, to illuminate and inflame you in the ſelf ſame liſt. Behold him who hath been refined above all others in the School of God, I mean <hi>Moyſes.</hi> Who hath been more humble in refuſing charges, more obedient in accepting them, more faithfull in exerciſing, more induſtrious in executing the commandments of God, more vigilant in government of the people, more ſevere in correction of vices, more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in ſufferance of the infirmities of Subjects, and more zealous in the cordial love he bare to the whole world?</p>
            <p>With theſe gifts he became the God of Monarchs, he ruined the State of his enemies, he unlooſed the chaines of an infinite number of ſlaves, he opened Seas, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nured wilderneſſes, he marched in the front of fix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand men at arms, he lived laborious amongſt Shepherds, chaſt in the Court of Kings, temperate in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56313:17"/>
a companion of Angels in his retirement, and as it were a cabinet-friend of God, having continually heaven for object, and all greatneſſe in contempt. He had blotted out all that was man in him, by the purity of a converſation wholy celeſtial. The fleſh was in him in ſuch ſubjection, and the ſpirit in ſuch Empire, that (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks, in his book of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel)</hi> he merited the name of God, in the reſemblance of whom he was transformed by the ſuperabundance of his vertues.</p>
            <p>Behold that great Diſciple of <hi>Moyſes, Joſue.</hi> What piety in the ſervice of the Omnipotent, what ſweetneſſe in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, what greatneſſe of ſpirit in noble enterprizes, what patience in difficulties, what prudence in direction, what diſpatch in expeditions? It is no wonder if in the fight of theſe eminent qualities, Walls and Cities fell, Giants waxed pale, Rivers retired back, the Sun ſtood ſtill, and one and thirty Kings underwent the yoke.</p>
            <p>Behold <hi>Samuel,</hi> the Father, Maſter, and Judge of two Kings, the Doctour of Prophets, the Sanctuary of the poor, the pillar of the Church. Is it not a magnificent ſpectacle to ſee him go out of charge, after ſo long a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſo great a diverſity of Affairs, with a heart ſo untainted, and hands undefiled, as if he had perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually converſed with Angels? Is it not a moſt heroical action, which he did in the firſt of Kings, when after the election of <hi>Saul,</hi> having voluntarily reſigned his Dignity, he ſhewed himſelf with upreard head in the midſt of the people, and gave liberty to all the world, from the leaſt to the greateſt, to complain and make information againſt him, before the King newly choſen? If it may be found that in his Magiſtracy, he ever did the leaſt wrong to any man, he is there ready to afford all ſatisfaction, that may be thought fit. But as he had lived moſt innocently, at this word was lifted up a loud cry, proceeding from a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent of the people, which highly proclaimed the integrity of his juſtice. Is not this a praiſe of more value then millions of Gold and Empires? But above all reflect often on the Wiſdome of God Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56313:17"/>
Jeſus Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the world, as the Prime model of all States-men, whom the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> hath exactly repreſented in the eleventh Chapter of his Prophecy; where he figureth the Redeemer unto us in the quality of a Judge, to ſerve for inſtruction and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for as much as concerneth his perfections, he gave him ſeven ſorts of ſpirits very conſonant to a true Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician; the ſpirit of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Counſel,</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Science,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> and the ſpirit of the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> wherewith he was wholly repleniſhed. Then, deſcribing the maner of his proceeding, ſaith, <hi>He ſhall not judge according to humane appearances, by the inconſiderate view of carnal eyes, and the relation of a raſh tongue; but he ſhall do juſtice to the poor, and fortifie himſelf with all kind of vigour, for the defence of ſo many gentle ſouls, as are oppreſſed in the world. To this purpoſe he ſhall ſtrike the earth with the words of his mouth, uſing his tongue as a rod of correction, and ſhall overthrow the wicked with the breath of his lips. Juſtice ſhall be ſo familiar to him, that he ſhall make uſe of it as a girdle of honour, or a rich baudrike, which brave Captains wear. The effects of his Government ſhall be ſo eminent, that under his raign the Woolf ſhall be ſeen to cohabit with the Lamb, the Leopard with the Goat, the Calf with the Lyon, and little Children to play with Baſilisks and Aſpicks.</hi> Willing in theſe Allegories to ſignifie how this divine Governour ſhould mollifie the moſt ſavage hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and reduce them to the temper of reaſon.</p>
            <p>I conclude here, my Lord, wiſhing it may be ſo in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> under your Government. That you may imitate this great Exemplar to Judges. That you may be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Samuel,</hi> a <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and a <hi>Moſes</hi> to the people under your charge. That in particular you may (in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conjuncture) have the charity and compaſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> for them all; ſince you know them (very neer) all, one way or other, guilty tranſgreſſors, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving either made, or followed, or adored the <hi>Gods of Gold.</hi> And (therefore) that, without loſing this laſt and beſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56313:18"/>
opportunity of your departure hence, which now is drawing on ſo neer, your Grace may be pleaſed to ſpeak your ſtrongeſt interceſſion for them all, to his Majeſty, and ſpeak it with that love, zeal and fervour <hi>Moſes</hi> did for his beloved <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to God (in the two and thirtieth of <hi>Exodus)</hi> when they had fallen into the moſt grievous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion imaginable. And that you may be pleaſed to ſpeak that interceſſion, even in the very words of this great Prophetical Commander, this Familiar of God. <hi>Either forgive them now their ſin, or if not, then (I beſeech thee) blot me out of thy book which thou haſt written. Aut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte eis hanc noxam: aut dele me de libro tuo quem ſcripſiſti.</hi> Wherein (my Lord) prevailing (as I doubt not you will) and obtaining this general Pardon from the moſt gracious, indulgent, merciful Prince on earth, and afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effectually the benefit thereof to all the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick people of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to ſo many other different parties and intereſts in that Kingdome, without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without prejudice to the rights of any of all (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which might be juſtly claimed by them from ſuch an Act of Indempnity and Oblivion, and, in purſuance thereof, from the equity of the Laws, and from his Majeſties other gracious Conceſſions in Articles of Peace) you will certainly give the moſt hopeful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning may be to your other glorious undertakings hereafter: as at preſent evict this confeſſion from all the world, that you have deafned your ears to the Enchanter of injuſtice, and that, ever conſtant to your ſelf, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member perpetually and follow this more Chriſtian, more humane precept of an Apoſtle, <hi>Vince in bono malum.</hi> Which is the vow for you of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Grace's moſt humble, most faithful, and moſt obedient Servant <hi>P. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56313:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
